Mss.Ms.Coll.76.17
American Philosophical Society
Henry Howard Houston, II Papers
1903-1918
Mss.Ms.Coll.76.17
American Philosophical Society
8.0 Linear feet
Henry Howard Houston II (1895-1918) was the son of a prominent Philadelphia family, the Houstons. He enjoyed a privileged upbringing, graduating from Chestnut Hill Academy in 1912 and from the University of Pennsylvania in 1916. Upon his graduation date, he enlisted in Battery C of the First Field Artillery, Pennsylvania National Guard, and was sent to the Texas and New Mexico borders in response to Pancho Villa's raids from Mexico. In January 1917, he volunteered with the American Field Ambulance Service in France during World War I, stationed near Verdun, where he was constantly under fire when performing his duty to pick up wounded soldiers from the trenches. Henry took a commission to serve with the French Army and enrolled in its transportation school. The French government awarded him the Croix de Guerre for gallantry under fire. When the U.S. entered the war, Henry resigned his commission in the French army and rejoined his Pennsylvania National Guard unit, the 53rd Field Artillery Brigade, 28th Division. He returned to the U.S., and received training as an aerial observer at Fort Sill, Oklahoma. It seems that, in early 1918, he returned a second time to France. In August 1918, German bombing squadrons attacked nightly, and Henry, then a lieutenant and personal aide to General Price, was killed south of Arcis-le-Ponsart while returning from an air field. He was 23. The bulk of this eight linear feet collection reflects Henry's personal life as a son, soldier, friend and lover, during the last three years of his life 1916 to 1918.
Houston, Henry Howard, II, 1895-1918
Biographical/Historical note
First Lieutenant Henry Howard Houston II, April 5, 1895-August 18, 1918. Born to Samuel Houston and Edith Atlee Corlies Houston in Chestnut Hill, Pennsylvania on April 5, 1895. His mother died days after his birth. Seven years later his father married Charlotte Harding Shephard Brown, who brought two children to the marriage. In 1910, Samuel and Charlotte welcomed the birth of their daughter, Eleanor.
'Hennie' as he was known, attended Chestnut Hill Academy and the University of Pennsylvania, graduating in 1916. He was a sailor and accomplished soccer player. He enlisted in Battery C of the First Field Artillery, Pennsylvania National Guard, the same day he graduated and was sent to the Texas and New Mexico borders in response to Pancho Villa's raids from Mexico. In January 1917, he volunteered for the American Field Ambulance Service in France. Stationed near Verdun, he was frequently under fire while performing picking up wounded soldiers. He took a commission to serve with the French army, and by invitation, enrolled in the French Army Transportation School. He was awarded the Croix de Guerre for gallantry under fire.
He resigned his commission when the United States entered the war and rejoined his Pennsylvania National Guard unit, the 53rd Field Artillery Brigade, 28th Division. He was trained as an aerial observer at Fort Sill, Oklahoma before returning to France. From France he wrote to his father in February 1918 about the School of Fire where he was receiving more training for aerial observation: "This is the branch of aviation for which all other branches exist. A fighting plane goes up merely to protect friendly observation planes and sink enemy craft. Artillery would be blind without aerial observation. By getting into this game I am not getting out of artillery but merely raising it to the 17th power. Don't worry, I won't get hurt."
Brigade Commander General William Price requested that the well-trained Lieutenant Houston serve on his staff as a personal aide. On August 18, 1918, Houston was killed south of Arcis-le-Ponsart while returning from an airfield. He had volunteered to go to the airfield for the purpose of establishing more thorough cooperation between the aerial observers and the heavy batteries of the 108th Field Artillery, whose fire they were then directing.
Henry Howard Houston, II is buried in the military cemetery in Suresnes, France. He was 23 years old when he was killed. In his honor, Henry's parents gave a stone building to the local American Legion and the building is named the Henry Howard Houston, 2nd Post.
Scope and Contents note
The Henry Howard Houston, II Series (1895-1918, bulk 1910-1918) consists of material from throughout Houtson's life, including school report cards, early letters to his parents, and photographs from his childhood and college days. However, the majority of the the material is from his time in the ambulance service and the military, mainly correspondence, photographs and other material from his time in France during World War I.
This series is rich in materials related to World War I history and early 20th century history of one of Philadelphia's most prominent families at that time, the Houstons. Those studying the regimental history of the 28th Division (Pennsylvania National Guard, "Iron Division") during World War I will find this collection valuable. Of special note is the correspondence between Henry and his parents, Samuel Frederic Houston and Charlotte Harding Houston. Also, of significance, a letter from Major General W.G. Price to Henry is included, dated February 15, 1918. In the Graphics Subseries are photographs of Henry and his division but also photographs from his time at Fort Bliss in Texas.
The material is organized into eight subseries: Correspondence; Military Communication; Personal; Bound Volumes; Printed Materials; Graphics; Maps; and Realia. Most of the series are arranged alphabetically, except where the Arrangement Note indicates otherwise.
Related Archival Materials note
Material about the life of Henry Houston, II, including condolence letters to his parents and information about the cemetery in which he is buried can be found in the Samuel Frederic Houston Papers, Series 18 of the Smith-Houston-Morris-Ogden Family Papers, Ms Coll 76.
Bibliography
A list of references pertaining to Henry Howard Houston II and the Houston family.
Contosta, David R. A Philadelphia Family: The Houstons and Woodwards of Chestnut Hill. Philadelphia: University of Pennsylvania Press, 1988. Print.
Houston, E. Rankin. History of the Houston Families and their Descendants 1450-1912 with a Genealogical Record. Carlisle: Carlisle Printing Company, 1912. Print.
Houston, Samuel Rutherford. Brief Biographical Accounts of Many Members of the Houston Family Accompanied by a Genealogical Table. Cincinnati: Elm Street Printing Company, 1882. Print.
Martin, Edward. The Twenty-Eighth Division Pennsylvania's Guard in the World War, Volume IV. Pittsburgh: 28th Division Publishing Co., 1924. Print.
Roberts Jr., Frank C. The Houstons of Philadelphia. New York: The Newcomer Society in North America, 1954. Print.
Houston, Charlotte; Houston, Samuel Frederick, 1866-1952; University of Pennsylvania; Philadelphia. Citizens; United States. Army--History--Punitive Expedition into Mexico, 1916; United States. Army--History--World War, 1914-1918; World War, 1914-1918 --Regimental histories --United States --28th (Iron) division; World War, 1914-1918--France; World War, 1914-1918--Regimental histories--United States
- Subseries A. Correspondence, 1901, 1906, 1916-1918
  Scope and Contents note
  The Correspondence sub-series consists mainly of Henry’s correspondence with his parents, Samuel F. Houston and Charlotte Harding Houston, while Henry served in the armed forces. The second largest category of letters comes from letters to and from his friends. There are a few touching letters between Henry and his youngest half-sister, Eleanor Houston.
  Arrangement note
  These letters are generally arranged alphabetically by the last name of the sender. Under that sender's last name, the letters are arranged chronologically. Where the last name of the sender is unclear, the letter is arranged alphabetically by the sender's first name.
  - Letter to Henry Howard Houston II, 1917 August 23; 1.0 item; Allen, W.
  - Letter to Henry Howard Houston II, 1918 January 6; 1.0 item; Andrews, D
    Letter from D. Andrews, Henry's friend, to Henry. Fraternity activities.
  - Letter to Henry Howard Houston II, 1917 October 17; 1.0 item; Bandellini, F
  - Bébé. Letter to Henry Howard Houston II, 1918 August 1; 1.0 item
    Brief letter of amorous nature. Year uncertain, but most likely 1918.
  - Letter to Henry Howard Houston II, 1917 May 7; 1.0 item; Coan, Ray
    Last name uncertain, could be "Coan" or "Coun."
  - Cousin. Letter to Henry Howard Houston II, undated; 1.0 item
    Letter written in a child's handwriting. Initialed "HHW" at the end.
  - Letter to Henry Howard Houston II, 1916 October 15; 2.0 items; Houston, Charlotte
  - Letters to Henry Howard Houston II, 1918 April-August; 5.0 items; Houston, Charlotte
  - Letters to Henry Howard Houston II, 1917 February 28, 1918 August 4; 3.0 items; Smith, Houston, Eleanor
  - Letter to Mrs. Graham, 1918 March 19; 1.0 item; Houston, Henry Howard, II, 1895-1918
  - Letter to Charlotte Houston, 1910 October 18; 1.0 item; Houston, Henry Howard, II, 1895-1918
  - Letters to Charlotte Houston, 1915 June-July; 5.0 items; Houston, Henry Howard, II, 1895-1918
  - Letters to Charlotte Houston, 1916 July-August; 5.0 items; Houston, Henry Howard, II, 1895-1918
  - Letters to Charlotte Houston, 1916 October-November; 4.0 items; Houston, Henry Howard, II, 1895-1918
  - Letters to Charlotte Houston, 1917 January-April; 11.0 items; Houston, Henry Howard, II, 1895-1918
  - Letters to Charlotte Houston, 1917 May-October, November; 10.0 items; Houston, Henry Howard, II, 1895-1918
    The year of the November letter is unknown, but most likely 1917.
  - Letters to Charlotte Houston, 1918 January-June; 9.0 items; Houston, Henry Howard, II, 1895-1918
  - Letter to Charlotte Houston, undated; 1.0 item; Houston, Henry Howard, II, 1895-1918
  - Letters to Charlotte Houston, undated; 1.0 item; Houston, Henry Howard, II, 1895-1918
  - Letters to Charlotte Houston, undated; 1.0 item
  - Letters to Eleanor Houston, 1910 August 5, 1917 January 16; 2.0 items; Houston, Henry Howard, II, 1895-1918
  - Letter to Mrs. Henry Howard Houston, Grandmother, 1903 July 19; 1.0 item; Houston, Henry Howard, II, 1895-1918
  - Letters to Eugénie Iselin, 1917 July,1918 July; 5.0 items; Houston, Henry Howard, II, 1895-1918
  - Letter to Harry Iselin, 1917 April 30; 1.0 item; Houston, Henry Howard, II, 1895-1918
    Letter to Cousin.
  - Letter to Harry Iselin, 1918 June 8; 1.0 item; Houston, Henry Howard, II, 1895-1918
  - Letter to Samuel F. Houston, 1915, July 11; 1.0 item
  - Letters to Samuel F. Houston, 1916 June-October; 9.0 items; Houston, Henry Howard, II, 1895-1918
  - Letters to Samuel F. Houston, 1917 January-March; 6.0 items; Houston, Henry Howard, II, 1895-1918
  - Letters to Samuel F. Houston, 1917 April-September; 5.0 items; Houston, Henry Howard, II, 1895-1918
  - Letters to Samuel F. Houston, 1918 February-July; 8.0 items; Houston, Henry Howard, II, 1895-1918
  - Letter to Santa Claus, 1901 November 25; 1.0 item; Houston, Henry Howard, II, 1895-1918
  - Letter to unknown, 1916; 1.0 item; Houston, Henry Howard, II, 1895-1918
    Composed in Albuquerque, New Mexico.
  - Telegram to unknown, 1917 August 13; 1.0 item; Houston, Henry Howard, II, 1895-1918
    Telegram sent from Paris, France.
  - Letters to Henry Howard Houston, II, 1917 January-February; 7.0 items; Houston, Samuel Frederick, 1866-1952
  - Letters to Henry Howard Houston, II, 1917 March-April; 5.0 items; Houston, Samuel Frederick, 1866-1952
  - Letters to Henry Howard Houston, II, 1917 May-June; 4.0 items; Houston, Samuel Frederick, 1866-1952
  - Letters to Henry Howard Houston, II, 1917 June-July; 5.0 items; Houston, Samuel Frederick, 1866-1952
  - Letters to Henry Howard Houston, II, 1918 July-August; 3.0 items; Houston, Samuel Frederick, 1866-1952
  - Letter to Henry Howard Houston, II, unknown; 1.0 item; Houston, Samuel Frederick, 1866-1952
    Letter fragment.
  - Letter to Henry Howard Houston, II, 1917 July 13; 1.0 item; Iselin, Helene
  - Nance. Letter to Henry Howard Houston, II, 1917 May 23; 1.0 item
  - Peg. Letter to Henry Howard Houston, II, 1917 June 30; 1.0 item
  - Letter to Henry Howard Houston, II, 1913 June 9; 1.0 item; Pilger, Richard
    General note
    Receipt for speeding ticket
  - Letter to Henry Howard Houston, II, 1918 February 15; 1.0 item; Price, Jr., W.G., Major General
  - Letter to unknown, 1.0 item; Rex, Hilary
    Henry was most likely the recipient of this Christmas card, because this card came from the U.S. Flying Corps and Henry was part of aerial observation.
  - Letter to Henry Howard Houston, II, 1917 November 11; 1.0 item; Thompson, Hank B.
  - Letter to Henry Howard Houston, II, 1918 July 29; 1.0 item; Trotter, Betty
  - Letter to Henry Howard Houston, II, 1916 February 15; 1.0 item; University of Pennsylvania
  - Letter to Henry Howard Houston, II, 1917 May 11; 1.0 item; Whitaker, Samuel
- Subseries B. Military Communications, 1916-1918
  The Military Communications sub-series mainly consists of official letters and telegrams to Henry from the War Department of the United States and the French military. They detail orders which transfer Henry to a different division or location, or promote Henry to a new position.
  These documents are arranged alphabetically by the first letter of an organization's name. For example, "W" for "War Department," and "F" for "French Military."
  - 7th Division, 1917 September; 1.0 item
  - 28th Division, 1917 August- 1917 October, 1918 February-1918 April 10; 11.0 items
    Correspondence from the Pennsylvania National Guard Division, 28th from multiple creators. Includes fitness report signed off by General W. G. Price.
    Pennsylvania. National Guard. Infantry Division, 28th.. -- Correspondence
  - 53rd Artillery Brigade, 1918 April 26-1918 July 10; 3.0 items
  - American Ambulance Hospital in Paris, undated; 2.0 items
  - Commonwealth of PA, Adjutant- General's Office, 1917 July 3; 1.0 item
  - French Military Correspondence, 1914, 1.0 item
  - French Military Correspondence, 1917 Folder 1 of 5, 4.0 items
  - French Military Correspondence, 1917 Folder 2 of 5, 7.0 items
  - French Military Correspondence, 1917 Folder 3 of 5, 1917 February 16-1917 July 25; 2.0 items
  - French Military Correspondence, 1917 Folder 4 of 5, 4.0 items; Davis, David J.
  - French Military Correspondence, 1917 Folder 5 of 5, 5.0 items
  - French Military Correspondence, undated Folder 1 of 2, 4.0 items
  - French Military Correspondence, undated Folder 2 of 2, 3.0 items
  - Houston, Henry Howard II Travel Documents to France, 1917, undated; 8.0 items
    Tickets and Pass
  - National Guard, Pennsylvania, 1917 June 29; 1.0 item
  - National Security League Certificate, 1916 April 10; 1.0 item
  - Ordnance Department, USA, 1917 December 18; 1.0 item
  - United States War Department Correspondence, 1916 October 28, 1918 January 24, 1918 March 26, undated; 7.0 items
- Subseries C. Personal, 1906-1912, 1916-1917
  The Personal sub-series consists of some of Henry’s personal effects. These include his handwritten draft of a poem in iambic pentameter while he was in grade school, and its published form in the school newsletter. There are also his handwritten notes while he took lessons in artillery mechanics during his time in the service. In the back of this sub-series, there are folders labeled “Ephemera.” These include invitations and programs to events in honor of the 28th Division, which Henry may likely have attended.
  This subseries is arranged alphabetically by the first letter of an organization's name. For example, "C" for "Chestnut Hill Academy," "U" for "University of Pennsylvania."
  - Battery "C", PA, Reception Program, 1916; 1.0 item
  - Chestnut Hill Academy. The Wissahickon (Publication), 1912; 1.0 item
  - Houston, Henry Howard II. Chestnut Hill Academy Report Cards, 1906-1912; 1.0 box 12 Folders
  - Houston, Henry Howard II. Immunization Certification, 1916 June 23; 2.0 items
  - Houston, Henry Howard II. Invitation for a Ball, 1917; 1.0 item
  - Houston, Henry Howard II. Poem "The Race" Hand Written, undated; 1.0 item
  - Houston, Henry Howard II. Receipt for Tailored Clothes, 1917 January 31; 1.0 item
  - Houston, Henry Howard II. School Papers, undated; 4.0 folders
    School Papers of Dr. Robert Bridges, the Poetry of Hanefield, Lawrence Hope, Rudyard Kipling, Henry Newbert, Alfred Noyes, Robert Service, and Francis Thompson
  - Houston, Henry Howard II. United States Map, undated; 3.0 items
    Colored with crayons
  - Menu in French of French Cuisine, [October] 1917; 1.0 item
  - University of Pennsylvania. Soccer Team, 1915 (News Clipping), 1915 March; 2.0 items
  - University of Pennsylvania Tickets and Brochures, 1911-1917; 12.0 items
- Subseries D. Bound Volumes, 1917-1918, and undated
  The items in this sub-series are arranged alphabetically.
  This sub-series of bound volumes contains a number of personal notebooks and journals. The bulk of the materials are notes and journals from his time in artillery school. There is also a type-written transcript of some of Henry's journal entries as well as an unused booklet of postcards from France.
  - Abbaye, N.- D. d'Igny Postcards, undated; 1.0 folder
  - Houston, Henry Howard Journal, Bulk, 1914-1915; 1914-1916; 1.0 item
    This black leatherbound journal contains Henry's concise journal entries. The majority of the entries are between 1914-1915; only a few a recorded in 1916.
  - Houston, Henry Howard Journal, 1917; 1.0 item
    This small red leatherbound journal contains lengthy entries by Henry during the time that he was stationed in France.
  - Houston, Henry Howard Poems, 1914; 1.0 item
    This large red leatherbound journal contains a few of Henry's poems written in his own hand. A poem on a looseleaf sheet of paper is folded within the journal. Three photographs of Henry's grave is also enclosed in the journal.
  - Houston, Henry Howard List of Card Recipients and Addresses, 1.0 item
    In a small notebook, a list of card recipients and their addresses is recorded in Henry's own hand.
  - Houston, Henry Howard Artillery Class Notes, unknown; 1.0 item
    This notebook contains copious notes on artillery machinery in Henry's own hand.
  - Houston, Henry Howard Artillery and Mechanical Class Notes in France, undated; 1.0 item
  - Houston, Henry Howard Field Gunnery Class Notes Fort Sill, Oklahoma, 1917; 1.0 item
  - Houston, Henry Howard Pocket Journal, Poetry Composition, and School Grades, undated; 1.0 folder
  - Houston, Henry Howard Transcript of Journal, 1917 March; 1.0 item
  - Zeta Psi's Memorial Certificate in Honor of Henry Howard Houston, II, 1918; 1.0 item
    This memorial certificate, issued by Zeta Psi, honors members of the Zeta Psi fraternity who gave their lives during World War I.
- Subseries E. Printed Materials, 1911-1962; 1.0 item
  This sub-series is arranged into boxes determined by subject matter. For example: those materials pertaining to France or the western front of World War I are included in the box labeled "France" and materials pertaining to Henry Howard Houston II as a student at the University of Pennsylvania are included in the box labeled "University of Pennslyvania. The contents of each box are organized alphabetically.
  This sub-series is a collection of printed materials covering a wide range of topics including information about the World War I and the Western Front, field artillery, the University of Pennsylvania, and newspaper clippings.
  - Subsubseries 1 - France, 1915, 1917, 1919, 1920
    This subsub-series of Printed Materials consists of published works relating to France and the western front of World War I.
    - Armistice Glade and Monument, unknown; 1.0 item
      A small booklet about the monument for the armistice built in France.
    - La Bataille de Verdun: un Guide, un Panorama, une Histoire, 1919; 1.0 item
      Publishing Info
      Clermont-Ferrand, Michelin & co, c1919. Print.
      Book detailing the Battle of Verdun. Book is in French. Contains dried and pressed flowers from Verdun.
      Battlefields--France--Verdun
    - La Belgique et l'Allemagne, 1915; 1.0 item
      Informational book about Belgians and Germans, in French. Contains a handkerchief.
      Londres: Imprime par Harrison et Fils, 1915. Print.
      Belgium; World War I -- Germany
    - Carnival for Wounded, 1917 July 14; 1.0 item
      Pamphlet detailing the events of a carnival/festival put on for the wounded. Pamphlet is in French.
    - Extracts from the History of the American field service in France, "Friends of France," 1914-1917, 1920; 1.0 item; American Field Service.
      Small booklet of extracts from the History of the American Field Service in France.
      Boston and New York, Houghton Mifflin company, 1920.
    - Nelson Doubleday Complete War Map of Western Europe, 1918; 1.0 item
      This is a printed, foldable pocket map of western Europe during World War I.
    - Rand Mcnally War Map of the French Front, unknown; 1.0 item
      This is a published, folded pocket map of the French front during World War I. It shows the battle lines of 1914 and 1918.
    - Rheims and the battle for its possession, 1919; 1.0 item
      Published book detailing the battle of Rheims. Contains dried and pressed flowers from Rheims.
      Clermont-Ferrand, Michelin & co, c1920. Print.
      Battlefields--France--Rheims
  - Subsubseries 2 - Miscellaneous, 1911, 1914-1918
    This subsub-series of Printed Materials consists of miscellaneous printed works either owned by or pertaining to Henry Howard Houston II. There are several religious texts (hymnals, prayer books, etc) along with a book he received as a gift, a newspaper, and two editions of a local Philadelphia newsletter.
    - The Prize of Life, 1914; 1.0 item; Grenfell, Wilfred Thomason
      Small book that was given to Henry Howard Houston II by his Aunt Martha.
      Boston, New York [etc.] The Pilgrim press [c1914] Print.
    - In Honour: An Elegy by a Father, 1915; 1.0 item
      Small booklet dedicated to a soldier who died at the battle of Ypres in 1915. Markings in the margins.
      London: Constable and Company LTD., 1915. Print.
    - Newsletter - The Wissahickon, 1912-1918; 1.0 item
      Two editions of "The Wissahickon" newsletter from April 1912 and November 1918.
    - Prayer Book and Hymnal, 1911 March 12; 1.0 item
      Small pocket sized prayer book and hymnal given to Henry Howard Houston II for his confirmation on March 12, 1911.
    - Prayer Book for Soldiers and Sailors, 1917; 1.0 item
      Prayer book given to Henry Howard Houston II by his sister Eleanor.
      Philadelphia: Bishop White Prayer Book Society, 1917.
    - Prayer Book - Intercessions for the Church: War Edition, 1914-1918; 1.0 item
      Prayer book. Containts a small picture and prayer insert.
    - Prayer book, 1917; 1.0 item
      very small prayer pamphlet.
    - New York Times, 1916 January 11; 1.0 item
      This is a folded edition of the New York Times newspaper dated January 11, 1916.
      Physical Characteristics and Technical Requirements note
      This document is folded and fragile. It is flagged in the box and should be looked at by the Conservation Department.
  - Subsubseries 3 - US Military, 1911, 1916, 1917, 1939, undated
    This subsub-series of Printed Materials contains documents and texts pertaining to the United States military, specifically Henry Howard Houston II's unit, the 28th division of the 53rd Field Artillery Brigade.
    - General Orders No. 32, 1916 July 28; 1.0 item; United States. War Dept.
      Pamphlet containing the War Department's general orders no. 32.